Guide to the D.T. Niles Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
D.T. Niles Papers
1907-1970
RG 260
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
This collection documents the life of D.T. Niles (1908-1970) who was a Sri Lankan Methodist minister, ecumenical leader, and evangelist. Niles held several positions in ecumenical leadership including Chairman of the Youth Department of the World Council of Churches, Chairman of the World Student Christian Federation, and General Secretary for the East Asia Christian Conference. The collection include correspondence and collected materials relating to Niles' work and personal life.
Niles, D. T. (Daniel Thambyrajah), 1908-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Niles papers were received with the archives of the Christian Conference of Asia. His personal papers were separated while the records relating to his leadership role in CCA remain in that collection (Record Group No. 237).
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1908 May 4 Daniel Thambirajah Niles was born in Tellippalai, Ceylon, the son of W.D. Niles a district judge, and comes from a long line of ministers
1933 Bachelor of Divinity from the United Theological College in India
1933-1936 Taught at Jaffna Central College
1935 December 25 Married Dulcie Solomons
1936 Ordained and appointed District Evangelist of the North District of the Methodist Church in Ceylon
1939-1940 Evangelism Secretary of the World Alliance of YMCA in Geneva
1941-1945 Secretary of the National Christian Council of Ceylon
1950-1953 Pastor at Maradana, Colombo
1946-1950 Pastor of the Methodist Church at Point Pedro
1949-1953 First Chairman of the World Council of Churches' Youth Department
1953-1959 Executive Secretary for the Department of Evangelism of the World Council of Churches
1953-1960 Chairman of the World Student Christian Federation
1953-1961 Principal of Jaffna Central College
1957-1968 General Secretary of the East Asia Christian Conference
1959-1960 H.E. Fosdick Professor of Union Theological Seminary, New York
1964-1968 Chairman of the Methodist Churches in the northern district of Sri Lanka
1968-1970 President of the Methodist Church in Sri Lanka
1970 July 17 Niles died from cancer at the Vellore Mission Hospital in India. He was survived by his wife, Dulcie; two children Dr. Preman Niles and Rev. Wesley Dayalan Niles
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the life of D.T. Niles who was a noted author, ecumenical leader, and evangelist in Sri Lanka. It is predominantly comprised of correspondence that varies from the personal to the business of leadership in ecumenical circles. The collection also features a small amount of correspondence to Niles' wife, Dulcie Niles, and his father, W.D. Niles. The Collected materials series is comprised mostly of news clippings that document D.T. Niles' travels and speaking engagements as an ecumenical leader and evangelist. It also includes biographical information on Niles' grandfather, Daniel Poor Niles, obituaries, and book reviews of Niles published material.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Family Papers
Ecumenists; Church work with students; Niles, D. T. (Daniel Thambyrajah), 1908-1970
- Correspondence
  - Niles, Dulcie to Niles, D.T., 1920-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bullough, H., 1925-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cash, Percy, 1925-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Niles family: Mercy to Dulcie, Elsie, Jefam, W.P., Preman, Jayam, and Chewan, 1925-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jayawardana, Pinto, 1925-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lockwood, Arthur, 1928-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - re. D.T. Niles entering study for ministry, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hudson, Anacca, 1931-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Marris, G. Stainton, 1932-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - re. D.T. Niles between W.H. Niles and Middleton Weaver, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - re. Niles' report to the Student Christian Association of India, Burma, and Ceylon on his work as the traveling secretary, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thorpe, W.H., 1933-1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Weaver, Middleton E., 1934-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - World Student Christian Federation, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bookwalter, L.G., 1936-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous letters to Niles, Dulcie, 1937-1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Moulton, H.K., 1937-1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - World Alliance of YMCA (mostly Tracy Strong), 1937-1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Andrews, C.F., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - International Missionary Council (William Paton and John R. Mott), 1938-1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Methodist Missionary Society, 1938-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jessop, Gilbert, 1938-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Baker, Elizabeth, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Conference of Missionary Societies in Great Britain and Northern Ireland (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Dore, Margaret, 1939-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters from various publishers, 1939-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letters from various people in the United Kingdom to W.D. Niles re. D.T. Niles' trip, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letters sent by D.T. Niles to W.D. Niles describing his travels in the United Kingdom, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - ?, Muriel, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Van Dusen, H.P., 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - World Council of Churches, 1939-1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Occasional correspondence, 1940-1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Europe YMCA, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - re. visits to United States of America includes news clippings and papers, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Bunker, Syd, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Jackson, G. Basil, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Cornish, H.R., 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Noble, W.J., 1946-1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Wilson, J.R., 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Nelson, Robert, 1947-1959 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Mendis, George, 1948-1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Newton, M.I., 1948-1968 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - D.T. Niles' visit to Europe and World Council of Churches Amsterdam Assembly, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Queen Wilhelmina of the Netherlands, 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - re. visit to Australia. Includes brochures and news clippings., 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Baker, A.J. Kendall, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Garret, John, 1952-1956 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - re. visit to New Zealand. Includes news clippings, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Deschner, John, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Newbigin, Lesslie, 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - de Soysa, Harold, 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - From Dayalan Niles to parents, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - re. Niles' appointment as the Harry Emerson Fosdick Visiting Professor at Union Theological Seminary, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - re. 25th anniversary of D.T. Niles' ministry, 21 May 1960 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Princeton spring lectures includes program, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Manikam, R. B., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - From D.T. Niles to Dulcie Niles, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Niles, Dulcie (during D.T. Niles' last illness). Includes misc correspondence., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Bereavement letters sent to Dulcie Niles upon D.T. Niles' death, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Letters to Dulcie Niles including funeral service program for D.T. Niles, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Letters to Preman and Dayalan Niles after the death of their mother, Dulcie Niles, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous correspondents, 1929-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
- Collected materials
  - Notebook, notes, life sketch, and papers of appreciation of D.P. Niles, 1907, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Tribute to Daniel Poor Niles by his son, W.D. Niles, letters of condolences, and obituaries, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Certificates, diplomas, and testimonials of D.T. Niles, 1934-1956 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - News clippings re. D. T. Niles' career, 1937-1964 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Student Christian movement of India, Burma, and Ceylon conference program and news clippings, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Reviews of D.T. Niles' books, 1938-1968 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Reviews of D.T. Niles' books, 1938-1968 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Tambaran team visit to the United Kingdom. Includes news clippings, programs, report, and scrapbook., 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Ceylon Bible Study Conference news clippings, 1940 July 16 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - A Desiring to be United Church report by the Secretary of the National Council of Churches of Ceylon, presented at the annual meeting of the council, 1943 March 27 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Nathaniel Niles: biographical information and news clippings, 1941, 1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - World Council of Churches Amsterdam Assembly opening service program and report, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - D.T. Niles' visit to the USA. Includes program from Yale Divinity School 47th Convocation because Niles delivered the Beecher Lecture., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - D.T. Niles' visit to United Kingdom news clippings, program, and handwritten note in Tamil, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Biographical information on Nathaniel Niles and Jordan Lodge by D.T. Niles, 1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Typescript article The Christian Mandate by D.T. Niles (published in The Pacific Journal of Theology, December 1969 no 33) (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Obituaries for D.T. Niles, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Tributes to D.T. Niles, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Biography of Wesley Duraiappa Niles by G.C. Niles, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Edited report re. YMCA and Student Christian Movement program, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Notes of Dulcie Niles and report of travel to Geneva in unknown publication, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Notes on "Poonamalee's message", undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Photographs of D.T. Niles, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Speeches of D.T. Niles, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Student Christian Movement of Singapore draft report, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)